<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[MJ Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://macrojames.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://macrojames.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-06-11T10:17:55+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://macrojames.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Macrojames]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting up]]></title>
    <link href="http://macrojames.github.com/blog/2012/06/11/starting-up/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-11T09:48:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://macrojames.github.com/blog/2012/06/11/starting-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After taking a <a href="http://yfrog.com/mgu3yphj">Photo</a> from my RPi, I started to flash my first SD-Card. I downloaded the <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads">Debian Squeeze Image</a> and deployed it to my tiny 2GB card.</p>

<pre><code>sudo dd if=/tmp/debian6-19-04-2012.img of=/dev/mmcblk0 bs=1M
</code></pre>

<p>Quite easy!
So I inserted the card into the RPi, connected the Pi via Ethernet to my notebook, took my old Nokia Micro-USB Charger supplying 1200 mA and powered it the first time. But that would have been to simple. I could neither connect
via the hostname &#8220;raspberrypi&#8221; nor via any IP address. I did not put the Pi into my existing Network and did not like to configure any additional DHCP services. Only solution was (I thought!) to plug an USB keyboard and try to
configure the network interface blindly. I could not attach any monitors because my TV in another room is the only device with HDMI inputs :(</p>

<p>With the network correctly configured, my ping requests were finally answered by the Pi.
But I still couldn&#8217;t connect via ssh. The almighty google search revealed that ssh is disabled on Raspberry Pi Debian images. Still typing blindly I tried</p>

<pre><code>sudo service ssh start
</code></pre>

<p>and it worked!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ordering the Pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://macrojames.github.com/blog/2012/06/06/ordering-the-pi/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-06T15:53:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://macrojames.github.com/blog/2012/06/06/ordering-the-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On February 29th 2012 early in the German morning, the Raspberry Pi killed both websites taking orders.
I was able to register at rs-online.com and express my demand in the Pi. In the mid of May I got an invitation to the exclusive Raspberry Pi shop at RS. Delivery was announced to start on June 7th or later.
But: Surprise! On May 31st my Pi was on its way from Birmingham and 25 hours later I had it in my hands. I was happy but it started to get painful.
More later&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
